Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Rufus Henry Fitzgerald, Administrative Files, 1945-1955 UA.2.10.1945-1955
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Business Administration, School of, 1947-1954 (Box 15, Folder 104)
  Changing degree from B.S. to Bachelor of Business Administration; Correspondence with Jan Novotny, of McGill University, regarding Joseph Macek employed to teach economics by the University. Novotny regarded Macek as a communist; Statement as to possibility of Scaife Company Scholarship; Management Problems for Executives, 1953
- B General (Box 15, Folder 105)
  Babcock estate; Donation of and acceptance of the Browne Room by Anna Moody Browne to be given to the University as a memorial to her parents, correspondence with Chancellor Bowman, 1944; Bevier, George M. – letter, signed, about receiving honorary degree from the University as well as other correspondence. Claralou Bonnar; Brookhaven meeting; Pamphlet on Ships paintings by Farnham; Broughton letter for Chien Ho; Buchannan donation of WWI books; Correspondence with Duncan Bruce regarding donation of Bruce materials (letterbook, painting and eyeglasses)- correspondence about Bruce family
- Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1949-1955 (Box 15, Folder 106)
  Correspondence on a survey "Developments of international significance at the University of Pittsburgh, 1950-1955; Proposed Educational Exchange Pilot Project; Report qLC1090 P693
- Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1938-1953 (Box 15, Folder 107)
- Carnegie Institute, Museum and Fine Arts (Box 15, Folder 108)
  Exhibition in memory of Dr. Avinoff; cross-reference on portrait of William Pitt; Short biography of Dr. Avinoff; Carnegie International, 1952 guest list; Corresp. re: Herbert Spencer bust by Ford
- Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1942-1955 (Box 15, Folder 109)
  Correspondence between Fitzgerald and Warner/Dougherty as well as material about CIT
- Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, 1944-1947 (Box 15, Folder 110)
- Cathedral of Learning, 1939-1951 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  Illumination of the Cathedral of Learning; Social activities allowed in the Commons Room; Classroom use for 1st-3rd floors; Material for guides to learn; History of the Cathedral of Learning and some of the Nationality Rooms; Electrachome picture, September 1949 (Not in file)
- Cast, James H., 1949-1950 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  Correspondence also some information about Washington and Jefferson College
- Chancellor's reception for parents of freshmen, 1945-1955 (Box 15, Folder 113)
- Chamber of Commerce, 1944-1955 (Box 16, Folder 114)
  Includes "Pittsburgh's 100 Young Men" dated 1953; CCP "Facts about Pittsburgh" Brochure
- Chaplain, 1952-1955 (Box 16, Folder 115)
  Heinz Chapel; Annual report of Chaplain, 1954; Dr. Emory E. Luccock – installation program, 1953; Policies governing Chapel, 1955
- Charter Day (February 28), 1946, 1947, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 116)
  Correspondence to get a speaker; one signature of John Foster Dulles; Charter Day program, 1946
- Cheating, 1948-1950 (Box 16, Folder 117)
  To publish once a year in University announcements the policy on dishonesty so professors also know; Suggested methods for dealing with the problem of cheating; Minutes of meeting of Committee to consider student cheating, 1948
- Chinese students, faculty, alumni (Box 16, Folder 118)
  Correspondence about Chen Li Fu (Chen Tsu Yen) visit; also with Kwoc Tung Fung
- Civic Club of Allegheny County, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 119)
  Exceptionally Able Youths, joint program with the University of Pittsburgh
- Civil Defense, 1950-1955 (Box 16, Folder 120)
  Mr. Viers W. Adams, chairman of University Civilian Defense Committee; Succeeded by Mr. Louis W.H. Johnston; Office building civil defense and disaster plan, Pittsburgh and Allegheny County; University Plans and procedures developed since December 1, 1950
- Clapp, George H. dinner, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 121)
  Program, menu and correspondence for the birthday dinner for Clapp
- Classrooms that Teach, 1941-1942 (Box 16, Folder 122)
  Thoughts of painting murals on classroom walls; correspondence with artists
- Clippings (Box 16, Folder 123)
  File is missing as of 07/07/2003; contained newsclipping and original speech in 1932 by General Douglas MacArthur
- College
- College, Dean's Office, 1951-1955 (Box 16, Folder 124)
  Stefan Lorant book and Leland Baldwin; Sun-Telegraph clipping of MacArthur speech; Interdepartmental major in Religion and in Far Eastern Studies
- College, Astronomy and Biology (Box 16, Folder 125)
  Wagman letter re: Sir Harold Spencer-Jones; Clippings on Peter Gray's "Michrotomists Formulary"
- College, Chemistry (Box 16, Folder 126)
  Silverman retirement letters; Clipping: Glass collection of Dr. Alexander Silverman given to another school; Dr. Silverman's biography in connection with the University; History of the Chemistry Department by Dr. Silverman; other memoranda about Chemistry Dept; C.G. King notes
- College, Classics, 1939-1952 (Box 16, Folder 127)
  Biographical outline of Arthur Milton Young; Correspondence about portrait of James Stinchcomb and an "In Memoriam"; other Classics memoranda
- College, English (Box 16, Folder 128)
  Letters from Lawrence Lee; Letter from George Crouch who was in England; Report on the Department, Spring 1944; Searching for a new Head for Department
- College, English, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 128a)
  Materials and clippings on the investigation of George Abbe regarding his membership in Progressive Citizens of America; clippings on Robert T. Harper from Carnegie Tech.
- College, Fine Arts, 1939-1955 (Box 16, Folder 129)
  Walter Hovey's letter from India, December 1954; clipping on the Cantini's Memo concerning the celebration of the 25th anniversary of the department; Collection of colored photographs of Blackfeet People – Walter McClintock – to be in Fine Arts; Two pamphlets by Walter McClintock, "Blackfoot warrior societies" and "Painted tipis and picture writing of the Blackfoot Indians"
- College, Geography, 1943-1952 (Box 16, Folder 130)
- College, Geology, 1940-1953 (Box 17, Folder 131)
  Memos from Dr. Richard E. Sherrill about Geology Dept., also files about his death; Smith sisters' Fund and for upkeep of the Smith cabinet of minerals; Smith donation to Allegheny Observatory; Leighton letter; Article "Master Draftsman" on Klauder.
- College, History, 1952-1955 (Box 17, Folder 132)
  Russell J. Ferguson, new head of Department 1955; John Oliver retirement; Reprint: Benjamin Franklin's Ohio Valley Lands, by Alfred P. James; Dr. George B. Fowler – correspondence about his research in Austria on manuscripts in monasteries, 1952; Walker papers; Navy history contract
- College, Humanities, 1938-1952 (Box 17, Folder 133)
  Pamphlet: Humanities Curriculum; 1938-39 correspondence from John Geise regarding Humanities Curriculum; Geise Air Force proposal
- College, Mathematics, 1944-1955 (Box 17, Folder 134)
  Computer Committee, Aviation Program, Class size study: 1930 vs 1946
- College, Modern Languages, 1945-1955 (Box 17, Folder 135)
  J.F.L. Raschen retirement and library collection (purchased by the University)
- College, Music, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 136)
  Change from Music Appreciation to Music; Score: Exultant Spirit, by Theodore M. Finney
- College, Philosophy (Box 17, Folder 137)
  "Tentative Thesis Towards a Theology" and "Report on a lecture tour in Germany, 1953-54," by Richard Hope; A philosophy for world unification, by Oliver L. Reiser, 1946; Department Brochure
- College, Physical Education, 1949-1954 (Box 17, Folder 138)
  Re-organization memos.
- College, Physical therapy, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 139)
  D.T. Watson School
- College, Physics, 1952-1954 (Box 17, Folder 140)
  Mary E. Warga named Distinguished Daughter of Pennsylvania, 1954; Memo from R.A. McConnell "Regarding attitudes among physicists toward ESP", 1952
- College, Political Science, 1952-1955 (Box 17, Folder 141)
  Retirement testimonial banquet; a tribute to Dr. Elmer D. Graper, by Louis W.H. Johnston, May 7, 1955; School for the elect, by Roy Kohler (Institute of Local Government (clipping); Study on politics by Falk Foundation
- College, Psychology, 1952-1954 (Box 17, Folder 142)
- Commencement and Convocations, June 1947-June 1950 (Box 17, Folder 143)
  1950: honorary degrees to Dr. Barbour, King and Anderson; 1949: honorary degrees to John Christian Warner, citations; 1948: honorary degrees to Elmer Allen Holbrook, Earl A. Dimmick; 1947: honorary degrees to George Frederick Zook; William Watson Smith; Richard King Mellon
- Commencements and Convocations, September 1950-June 1952 (Box 17, Folder 144)
  1950: no honorary degrees; 1951: honorary degrees to Robert Livingston Johnson; Philip Showalter Hench; Milton Stover Eisenhower; Omar Nelson Bradley; citations; 1952: honorary degrees to Roy Carnegie McKenna; Henry B. Higgins; Eli Lilly; Leon Falk, Jr.; Arthur Stanton Adams
- Commencement, August 1952-August 1954 (Box 17, Folder 145)
  1953: honorary degrees to John Christian Warner; James Henderson Duff; Clarence Edward McCartney; Ben Moreell; Louis Tomlinson Benezet; James Childs Rea; 1954: honorary degrees to Gustav L. Schramm; John Grier Buchanan; Rachel McMasters Miller Hunt; Adolph William Schmidt; Reuben G. Gustavson; George Magoffin Humphrey
- Commencement, February 1955 (Box 18, Folder 146)
  Honorary degree, William S. Thomas
- Commencement, June 1955 (Box 18, Folder 147)
  Honorary degrees to Harlan Henthorne Hatcher; Mabel Lindsay Gillespie; Jonas Edward Salk; Vira Ingham Heinz; Sir Roger Mellor Makins; Sarah Mellon Scaife; Chief Justice Earl Warren; Rugus Henry Fitzgerald; Citations; Correspondence with honorary degree recipients; Newspaper clippings and pictures (moved to groups – commencement – 1955 Photo file); Luncheon guest list
- Commencement, August 1955 (Box 18, Folder 148)
  Program, tally of graduates and clippings
- Commencement, 1945-1947 (Box 18, Folder 149)
  1947, February and June honorary degrees: Arthur Emil Braun, George Hubbard Clapp, William Robertson Farmer; 1946, February and June honorary degrees: Oliver Cromwell Carmichael, Augustus Kountze Oliver, Guy Everett Snavely; 1945, January and May honorary degrees; School of Dentistry; School of Medicine
- Commencement, 1943-1944 (Box 18, Folder 150)
  1944, May (honorary degree: George William McClelland) and January; 1943, June (honorary degree: Henry Harrington Hill) and September; 1943, February (honorary degree: Ralph Dorn Hetzel)
- Commencement, 1938-1942 (Box 18, Folder 151)
  1942, honorary degree: Ralph Cooper Hutchinson; 1941, program; instructions to seniors; Bibliography on commencement activities and programs, comp. by Lorena A. Garloch; 1940, honorary degrees: Franklyn Bliss Snyder, Douglas Fuller Miner, Ralph Munn; 1939; 1938
- Commons Room Symbols (Box 18, Folder 152)
  Committee on art symbols for the Cathedral; Committee on Medallions; Layout for carving (blue print)
- Community Chest, 1952-1954 (Box 19, Folder 153)
- Communications (Box 19, Folder 154)
  Plan for development of a communications program; Memo to Communications Committee
- Comptroller, 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 155)
  Retirement Fund; Student Union Fee & part-time students; Travel expenses; Commissioner of Internal Revenue for tax exemption for fees collected from patients by doctors at the Health Center; Endowment on 3/3/1955; For 1954: total employees, total salaries, total withholding tax (from IRS); List of gifts and grants, December 1, 1954 to January 5, 1955; Procedure for appointment of all personnel; Tuition receipts, September 1954; University Food Services report; Loan from New York Life Insurance Co.; Tuition increases; Town Hall site (renamed Mellon tract)
- Comptroller, 1951-1953 (Box 19, Folder 156)
  Bonding of officers; Scholarship Endowment Fund; Engineering Building contract (between Thaw Hall & Old Mellon Institute) with Dick Corporation, 1953; University Food Service report; Financial reports: Book store, Printing Department, 1953; DeSota Hall financial report, July 1, 1952-June 30, 1953; Food Service Reports; Hispanic-American Room suggested, June 1953; Senatorial Scholarships, 938 for 1953; Monetary Gifts received, December 9, 1952-January 9, 1953; Graduate Student assistants – change in pay; Receipts from tuition and student activity fees, 1950/51; Nurses' Home under construction by Trimble Co. under agreement August 21, 1950
- Comptroller, 1948-1950 (Box 19, Folder 157)
  Social security, 1950; Buildings & Grounds budget; Mr. Monteverde and proper letters, 1950; Additions to endowment from July 1, 1945; Buildings & Ground job orders; Stadium activities, statement of income and expenses, 1948/49; Veterans Administration site sold by University to U.S. Government for $150,000 May 25, 1949, July 12, 1949; Schenley-Croghan Room, costs for restoration, 4/27/1949; Maturity of Stadium Bonds, December 1, 1949; Temporary loans during summer
- Congress of the United States. Committee to investigate tax exempt foundations (Box 19, Folder 158)
  Statement of Rockefeller Foundation and The General Education Board; The Ford Foundation, July 16, 1954; Questionnaire on Foundation support; Foundation support in the fields of the social sciences, 1929-1953
- Conservation Foundation (Box 19, Folder 159)
- Council for Financial Aid to Education (Box 20, Folder 160)
  Leaflets and some correspondence
- C (General) (Box 20, Folder 161)
  Castle, C. Woodrow charges and investigation, 1952; Copies of bills for furniture for the Chancellor's office; Oil painting "Pittsburgh in 1806", by George Beck – description in "Pitt" Spring, 1948 p. 24-31; Agreement between the University of Pittsburgh and Children's Hospital; Memos and leaflets about the rise of a local communist party; Community Church services for Heinz Chapel during Summer
- Deans Meeting Minutes, July 1954-1955 (Box 20, Folder 163)
- Deans Meeting Minutes, July 1947-June 1950 (Box 20, Folder 164)
- Deans Meeting Minutes, July 1946-June 1947 (Box 20, Folder 165)
- Deans Meeting Minutes, July 1943-June 1946 (Box 20, Folder 166)
- Deans Meeting Minutes, June 1941-June 1943 (Box 20, Folder 167)
- Deans Meeting Minutes, January 1939-June 1941 (Box 20, Folder 168)
  Proposal to establish non-credit courses for adults, 1941; Departmental collections of books, which Dr. Leland Baldwin seeks to remove from our catalog and have only an inventory (1940); Scholarship aid grants (1939)
- Dean of Men, September 1954-May 1955 (Box 20, Folder 169)
- Dean of Men, 1943-1954 (Box 20, Folder 170)
  "Battle Song" copyright to be renewed?; Biography 1952 of Theodore William Biddle; Band instruments, 1945; Marshalls and Guide service, 1945; Veterans returning to school; correspondence on subject of student activities
- Dean of Men, 1938-1943 (Box 21, Folder 171)
  Placement Bureau for Men, report, 1942/43; Policy for messages for students; Memos concerning War Efforts; 1942, theft of examination questions, Geology Department; Pittsburgh zoning regulations; Taxation on fraternities; Housing for students; Report of work done by the Dean of Men's Office
- Dean of Women (Box 21, Folder 172)
  Elizabeth Arden to visit campus and address women, 1952; Vacation for staff, 1950; Chinese Nationality Room – celebration of Independence Day, October 30, by giving an orange to each student; Women's Day, 1947 program in Stephen Foster Hall (Eve Curie the speaker); Heinz Chapel – bride's dressing room (Mrs. Heinz interested in supplying); Housing needed for women; Pin given (WRP-1900) by Mrs. John M. Phillips which had belonged to her brother, Dr. James H. K. Duff (1945); Report by the Information Office, 1944; Report on conditions of the Tuck Shop, 1943; An introduction to the art of living for Freshmen women, a syllabus for teachers by Thrysa W. Amos
- School of Dentistry, 1947-1954 (Box 21, Folder 173)
  Dr. William F. Swanson named Dean; Needs of the School; Annual Conference on Dental Health Programs; Correspondence; Dr. Lawrence Edward Van Kirk, Memorial to October 1953; Space problem in letter from the State Examining Board (move Printing Dept. out); Policies of the School, 1947; Dean H. Edmund Friesell, In memoriam 1946
- Discipline cases, 1940-1948 (Box 21, Folder 174)
  Access Restrictions
  Restricted.
  Janet Neesham; Michael A. Walek; Walter Zischkau
- Dormitories, 1944-1949 (Box 21, Folder 175)
- Duquesne University, 1951 (Box 21, Folder 176)
  Taping of Organ Concerts in Heinz Chapel
- D (General) (Box 21, Folder 177)
  Daufenback, William, Award of merit, May 1949; Daugherty, Dr. Carroll, Request for information by Jones and Laughlin, 1949; Rufus H. Fitzgerald Commencement speaker, 1954 at Davidson College; RHF sat for portrait by Sidney Dickinson, 1955; Rules for DeSota Hall dormitory, 1949; Clayton Braun, painter, letters about Brackenridge painting Sidney E. Dickinson, painter, - letters to Chancellor Fitzgerald about painting his portrait (handwritten); Dinner given 1954 for the Distinguished Daughters of Pennsylvania, by the University of Pittsburgh in the Commons Room, sponsored by Gimbels
- Editor, University of Pittsburgh Press (Starrett) (Box 21, Folder 178)
  Research and publication programs – Buhl Foundation Grants; Promotion efforts of the Press; Cresap report on the University Press; Stockton family gifts from Mrs. Sumner B. Ely (list of five)
- School of Education, 1951-1955 (Box 22, Folder 179)
  Yeager, William A. – Nature and determination of the total service load of faculty members in Schools (Colleges) of Education; Conference on Educational Leadership and Special Education Services, 1955; Search fro Dean for School of Education; Cooperative Program in Educational Administration, a report; How to choose your college, by Dr. Paul Masoner; Progress in the development of the internship program in School Administration, 1953/54; Report of the Committee on the Five-Year plan of the School of Education; Pittsburgh Area Workshop on Economic Education, 1953; Cooperative Program in Education and Administration – Penn State, University of Pennsylvania, University of Pittsburgh, and Temple; Final Report of the Committee of Five: The School of Education, its past, present and future, 1955
- Committee on Educational Exchange (Box 22, Folder 180)
  University of the Andes case, 1955; Educational Exchange awards, 1955/1954; Correspondence concerning the students from Columbia who are enrolled at the University of Pittsburgh; Need for arrangements for entertaining of foreign visitors, budget and full-time staff, etc. – letter from Louis W.H. Johnston, 1954; Foreign students, list of, 1953/54; Foreign Professors, 1953/54; Minutes of the Committee, October 26, 1953; & December 12, 1953; Correspondence concerning Committees for Syria Lebanon room, 1947; Committee on Educational Exchange – Statement of purpose and Program, 1948; (Name to be Committee on International Educational Exchange); qLC1090 P6923 report for Carnegie Endowment
- Ellsworth Center (Box 22, Folder 181)
  University of Pittsburgh at Ellsworth Center – Director, Dr. Viers Adams; Started in fall of 1947 (2 year center); Activities at the Ellsworth Center; Court case relative to flood lights which the University wants to install; Pamphlet announcing the opening of Ellsworth Center, September 1947; General policies affecting the operation of the Center
- Emory University (Box 22, Folder 182)
  Visit to by Chancellor Fitzgerald; Address by David Rockefeller April 12, 1955 – "The role of business in financing higher education"
- School of Engineering (Box 22, Folder 183)
  New building in progress; Interesting fact concerning the Schools of Engineering and Mines; Funds needed for the new building 1954; Proposed program for the development and improvement of the Schools of Engineering and mines, 1954; pamphlet: Engineering as a career; Dr. G.R. Fitterer appointed Dean of the Schools of Engineering & Mines; Engineers' Council for Professional Development – Summary of visiting panel report of the University of Pittsburgh, January 9, 1950; List of graduates of the metallurgical engineering Department, 1907-1947
- Erie Center (Erie Junior College) (Box 22, Folder 184)
  Report on the Erie Center, submitted by Lee M. Thurston, May 24, 1943
- Extension Division (Box 22, Folder 185)
  Community Church Services in Heinz Chapel, 1955; Summer Session, 1955 – The role of communications in human relations; Survey of community services on the University campus, 1953/54; Cresap Report and the Extension Division; Duties of the Director of Special Services from Viers W. Adams to the Chancellor; Suggested having a Director of Television; Purpose of the Extension Division, 1953; plan to establish Jr. college in Pittsburgh, 1946
- E (General) (Box 22, Folder 186)
  Electronic Computer Committee; Emergencies; Engineering Council (Proposed plan for development and improvement of the Schools of Engineering & Mines); Question of having the National Engineering Society in Pittsburgh, 1954; Pamphlet: Logical location for the new Engineering Center Building is Pittsburgh; Photograph of the proposed Engineering Society Building
- Falk School (Box 23, Folder 187)
- Film Library (Box 23, Folder 188)
  Committee recommends having a University Film Library and Service center, 1945
- Foreign Students, 1945-1951 (Box 23, Folder 189)
  List of students enrolled, 1951; 1950-51; 1947-48; 1946; 1945; 1944/45
- Stephen Foster Memorial (Box 23, Folder 190)
  Correspondence between Chancellor Fitzgerald and Fletcher Hodges, 1954; Program of 26th annual memorial program, 1953; Regulations for programs presented by organizations other than the University of Pittsburgh; Gifts from the Lilly family to the Foster Hall; Pamphlet: Stephen Collins Foster memorial; dedicated June 2, 1937
- Fund for the Advancement of Education (Box 23, Folder 191)
  Ford Foundation; Announcement of faculty fellowships, 1952/53
- F (General) (Box 23, Folder 192)
  Fair Employment Practices Ordinance, 1953; Ford Foundation, foreign study research fellowships, 1952; Ford Motor Co. scholarship program; Robert N. Farr; Gov. John Fine; Foreign Policy Seminars; Fraternities
- Graduate School, July 1954-June1955 (Box 23, Folder 193)
  Clippings – Dean Herbert E. Longenecker leaving for University of Illinois; "University faculty compensation policies and practices in the U.S.", by Herbert E. Longenecker; Report for the Committee on Outside Activities, prepared by Herbert E. Longenecker
- Graduate School, June 1953-June 1954 (Box 23, Folder 194)
  Statement on research at the University of Pittsburgh, by H.E. Longenecker, 1954; Study of remunerative outside activities of University Faculty members; Statement of the University of Pittsburgh in support of a proposal of Mellon Institute to house, maintain and operate a digital computer for the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, 1952
- Graduate School, 1943-1952 (Box 23, Folder 195)
- Graduate School, 1940-1941 (Box 23, Folder 196)
  New graduate school regulations as passed by the Executive Committee
- G (General) (Box 23, Folder 197)
  Addison Gibson Laboratory – report of activities; Gift of photograph of class of 1898 by Stella and Margaret Stein; List of Gillespie monetary gifts to the University; Greek Week celebration; Dr. Alan Gregg – Medical Institutes, 1953; Guggenheim Foundation; 1898 class photo-file contains names on photo; Greek Earthquake Committee; Graduate Hall; Alan Gregg speech; Ralph Griswold letter; Grove letter re: First Nations classroom
- Heinz Chapel (Box 23, Folder 198)
  Copy of deed of gift, 1929; Policies governing the uses of the Heinz Memorial Chapel; Stokowski to lead chorus in Heinz Chapel, 1951; Permission to use for weddings and the regulations, 1943; Charles J. Connick designed stain glass windows; Descriptive guide booklet; memorial service April 18, 1941 for Doctor Hugo Kahl; Annual report, 1949/50; Dedication program November 20, 1938